<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE Summary SYSTEM "Summary.dtd">
<Summary xmlns:cdr="cips.nci.nih.gov/cdr">
 <CdrDocCtl>
  <DocId><?xm-replace_text {
         The document ID will be assigned automatically
         }?></DocId>
  <DocTitle><?xm-replace_text {
         The document title will be constructed automatically
         }?></DocTitle>
 </CdrDocCtl>
 <SummaryMetaData>
  <SummaryType>Treatment</SummaryType>
  <SummaryAudience>Patients</SummaryAudience>
  <SummaryLanguage>English</SummaryLanguage>
  <SummaryDescription><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter a summary description (required)
         }?></SummaryDescription>
  <SummaryURL cdr:xref=""><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter Cancer.gov's pretty URL (required)
         }?></SummaryURL>
  <PDQBoard>
   <Board cdr:ref="CDR0000028327">PDQ Adult Treatment Editorial Board</Board>
  </PDQBoard>
  <MainTopics>
   <Term>Screening for X cancer</Term>
  </MainTopics>
  <SecondaryTopics>
  </SecondaryTopics>
 </SummaryMetaData>

 <SummaryTitle>Template: Screening for X Cancer</SummaryTitle>
 <SummarySection>
  <Title>What is screening?</Title>
  <Para>Screening is looking for cancer before a person has any symptoms. 
         This can help find cancer at an early stage. When abnormal 
         tissue or cancer is found early, it may be easier to treat. 
         By the time symptoms appear, cancer may have begun to spread.</Para>
  <Para>Scientists are trying to better understand which people are 
         more likely to get certain types of cancer. They also study the 
         things we do and the things around us to see if they cause cancer. 
         This information helps doctors recommend who should be screened 
         for cancer, which screening tests should be used, and how often 
         the tests should be done.</Para>
  <Para>It is important to remember that your doctor does not necessarily 
         think you have cancer if he or she suggests a screening test.
         Screening tests are given when you have no cancer symptoms.</Para>
  <Para>If a screening test result is abnormal, you may need to have more 
         tests done to find out if you have cancer. These are called 
         diagnostic tests.</Para>
  <Para>Refer to the following PDQ summaries for information about 
         prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of X cancer.</Para>
  <ItemizedList Compact="No" Style="bullet">
   <ListItem><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter link title
         }?></ListItem>
   <ListItem><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter link title
         }?></ListItem>
  </ItemizedList>
 </SummarySection>

 <SummarySection>
  <Title>General Information About X Cancer</Title>
  <SummarySection>
   <SectMetaData>
    <SectionType>Cancer description</SectionType>
    <SectionType>Organ description</SectionType>
   </SectMetaData>
   <KeyPoint>X cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells 
         form in the x.</KeyPoint>
   <Para><?xm-replace_text {
         Compose from treatment summary
         }?></Para>
  </SummarySection>
  <SummarySection>
   <SectMetaData>
    <SectionType><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter section type
         }?></SectionType>
   </SectMetaData>
   <KeyPoint><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter incidence keypoint
         }?></KeyPoint>
   <Para><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter text
         }?></Para>
  </SummarySection>
  <SummarySection>
   <SectMetaData>
    <SectionType>Risk factors</SectionType>
   </SectMetaData>
   <KeyPoint>A, B, and C can affect the risk of developing x cancer.</KeyPoint>
   <Para>Anything that increases the chance of getting a disease is 
         called a risk factor. Having a risk factor does not mean 
         that you will get cancer; not having risk factors doesn't 
         mean that you will not get cancer. People who think they may 
         be at risk should discuss this with their doctor. Risk factors 
         for x cancer include the following: 
         <Comment>Take from treatment summary</Comment></Para>
   <ItemizedList Compact="No" Style="bullet">
    <ListItem><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter risk factor
         }?></ListItem>
    <ListItem><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter risk factor
         }?></ListItem>
   </ItemizedList>
  </SummarySection>
 </SummarySection>

 <SummarySection>
  <Title>X Cancer Screening</Title>
  <SummarySection>
   <SectMetaData>
    <SectionType><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter section type
         }?></SectionType>
   </SectMetaData>
   <KeyPoint>Tests are used to screen for different types of cancer.</KeyPoint>
   <Para>Some screening tests are used because they have been shown to 
         be helpful both in finding cancers early and in decreasing the 
         chance of dying from these cancers. Other tests are used because 
         they have been shown to find cancer in some people; however, it 
         has not been proven in clinical trials that use of these tests 
         will decrease the risk of dying from cancer.</Para>
   <Para>Scientists study screening tests to find those with the fewest 
         risks and most benefits. Cancer screening trials also are meant 
         to show whether early detection (finding cancer before it causes 
         symptoms) decreases a person's chance of dying from the disease. 
         For some types of cancer, the chance of recovery is better if 
         the disease is found and treated at an early stage.</Para>
   <Para>Clinical trials that study cancer screening methods are taking 
         place in many parts of the country. Information about ongoing 
         clinical trials is available from the 
         <ExternalRef cdr:xref="http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials">NCI Web
         site</ExternalRef>.</Para>
  </SummarySection>

  <SummarySection>
   <KeyPoint># tests are commonly used to screen for x cancer:</KeyPoint>
   <SummarySection>
    <KeyPoint><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter test
         }?></KeyPoint>
    <Para><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter description of test
         }?></Para>
   </SummarySection>
   <SummarySection>
    <KeyPoint><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter test
         }?></KeyPoint>
    <Para><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter description of test
         }?></Para>
   </SummarySection>
  </SummarySection>
  <SummarySection>
   <KeyPoint>Other screening tests are being studied in clinical 
         trials.</KeyPoint>
   <SummarySection>
    <KeyPoint><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter test
         }?></KeyPoint>
    <Para><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter description of test
         }?></Para>
   </SummarySection>
   <SummarySection>
    <KeyPoint><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter test
         }?></KeyPoint>
    <Para><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter description of test
         }?></Para>
   </SummarySection>
   <Para>Screening clinical trials are taking place in many parts of 
         the country. Information about ongoing clinical trials is 
         available from the 
         <ExternalRef cdr:xref="http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials">NCI Web 
         site</ExternalRef>.</Para>
  </SummarySection>
 </SummarySection>

 <SummarySection>
  <Title>Risks of X Cancer Screening</Title>
  <SummarySection>
   <SectMetaData>
    <SectionType><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter section type
         }?></SectionType>
   </SectMetaData>
   <KeyPoint>Screening tests have risks.</KeyPoint>
   <Para>Decisions about screening tests can be difficult. Not all 
         screening tests are helpful and most have risks. Before having 
         any screening test, you may want to discuss the test with your 
         doctor. It is important to know the risks of the test and whether 
         it has been proven to reduce the risk of dying from cancer.</Para>
  </SummarySection>

  <SummarySection>
   <KeyPoint>The risks of x cancer screening include the following:</KeyPoint>
   <SummarySection>
    <KeyPoint>False-negative test results can occur.</KeyPoint>
    <Para>Screening test results may appear to be normal even though x 
         cancer is present. A person who receives a false-negative result 
         (one that shows there is no cancer when there really is) may 
         delay seeking medical care even if there are symptoms.</Para>
   </SummarySection>

   <SummarySection>
    <KeyPoint>False-positive test results can occur.</KeyPoint>
    <Para>Screening test results may appear to be abnormal even though 
         no cancer is present. A false-positive test result (one that 
         shows there is cancer when there really isn't) can cause anxiety 
         and is usually followed by more tests and procedures (such 
         as <?xm-replace_text {
         Enter tests specific to the cancer
         }?>), which also have risks.</Para>
   </SummarySection>
  </SummarySection>
 </SummarySection>

 <SummarySection>
  <SectMetaData>
   <SectionType>Changes to summary</SectionType>
  </SectMetaData>
  <Title>Changes to This Summary (MM/DD/YYYY)</Title>
  <Para>The PDQ cancer information summaries are reviewed regularly 
         and updated as new information becomes available.  This section 
         describes the latest changes made to this summary as of the 
         date above.</Para>
  <Para>
   <StandardWording>This summary was completely reformatted and 
         some content was added.</StandardWording>
  </Para>
 </SummarySection>
 <PatientVersionOf><?xm-replace_text {
         Select title of HP version
         }?></PatientVersionOf>
 <WillReplace><?xm-replace_text {
         Optionally link to the summary to be replaced by this document
         }?></WillReplace>
 <DateLastModified><?xm-replace_text {
         Enter date
         }?></DateLastModified>
</Summary>
